<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jeanoskii.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jeanoskii.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-07T00:28:43+00:00</updated><id>https://jeanoskii.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hello, world!</title><link href="https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/first/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello, world!"/><published>2026-01-06T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-06T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/first</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/first/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my blog, where I post just about computer stuff (mostly). My current interests are on computers, programming, cybersecurity, gaming, and of course teaching.</p> <p>First of all, why make a blog? I figured that a blog on my website would be the best avenue for me to share my thoughts, opinions, and experiences. Here, I have control of the content and the way I want to present them. But people might wonder: How about Facebook or X? Well, I am privacy-conscious. I have always limited my social media use. When I’m not chatting with my friends on Messenger, I’d be checking Facebook marketplace, and that’s it. As a matter of fact, the marketplace would be the primary reason I’m not deactivating my Facebook account yet; such good deals!</p> <p>Now let’s talk how I went about creating this blog.</p> <p>There are numerous ways one can create a blog nowadays, from dedicated blogging platforms to completely custom blogs. I’m too frugal to subscribe to popular blogging platforms, but I’m also too lazy to code a blog from scratch. Then I remembered <strong>Github Pages</strong>; I used it to teach pull-based development where my students forked my Github <a href="https://github.com/jeanoskii/Software-Design-Prefinal-Exam">repository</a> and appended their own entry into the <a href="https://jeanoskii.github.io/Software-Design-Prefinal-Exam/">site</a>.</p> <p>However, Github Pages only allows static websites—no Wordpress here! I had to look for a static site generator, narrowing down my choices to Astro, Hugo, and Jekyll. Each option uses different programming languages: Javascript, Go, and Ruby respectively (all of which I know little of). But I had to choose, and since Jekyll has built-in support for Github Pages, I went with <strong>Jekyll</strong>. This meant I had to brush up on my Ruby skills.</p> <p>During college, we had a course on web development where we created an application using plain Ruby and Ruby on Rails. But that memory is a bit hazy. At this point, my priority is to publish a blog, not learn Ruby <em>to</em> publish a blog. So I looked into Jekyll themes, coming up with <a href="https://github.com/cotes2020/jekyll-theme-chirpy/">Chirpy</a> and <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/">al-folio</a>. Both themes frequented my search, but the choice boiled down to which one has better documentation and community support. Having an easy to understand documentation meant that I can set up, configure, and run my blog just by reading the manual; and a good community meant that more people could help me fix my terrible code. Therefore, I went with <strong>al-folio</strong>.</p> <p>So the tech stack goes like this:</p> <pre><code class="language-mermaid">flowchart LR
    Github Pages --&gt; Jekyll --&gt; al-folio
</code></pre> <p>With this setup, I can quickly create a website while pretending to be coding in VS Code!</p> <p>As 2025 was ending, I kept thinking to myself that I needed to build a personal website. As 2026 starts, here I am with a finished blog post. Here marks the first out of the many posts in this blog. I am eager to share my knowledge, findings, and ramblings, only here on Jeano’s Journal.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="explainer"/><category term="blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My first blog post]]></summary></entry></feed>