<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jeanoskii.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jeanoskii.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-14T10:00:29+00:00</updated><id>https://jeanoskii.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website, project portfolio, and blog with topics on cybersecurity and computers. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Watch me on Youtube</title><link href="https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/tutorials/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watch me on Youtube"/><published>2026-01-11T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-11T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/tutorials</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/tutorials/"><![CDATA[<p>A favorite pastime of mine is watching video essays about niche topics related to computing. A few examples would be: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dnHdqPBrtH8">Why the Soviet Computer Failed</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BUCZJWo9MZo">Man and Computer: A Perspective</a>, and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=54CyHBI1d6Y">Xerox - The Company That Threw Away Everything</a>. I like the idea of feeding my brain with obscure information. Eventually, this habit would pay off while I was lecturing for STI. During class, I would refer to these bizarre examples, often to the astoundment of the students.</p> <p>The other night, I was watching a video essay on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MBHX3NvRARc">ThinkPad – The Story of the World’s Most Famous Laptop</a>. A memory came flashing back—I used to do this! I was making Youtube videos before, albeit of low production quality. Although, my content creation strategy was primarily driven either by a course requirement, or as supplementary teaching materials.</p> <p>So let’s take a trip down memory lane!</p> <p>2016—our journey begins here. This was the year when I first started working in a corporate job, and it was also the year I enrolled in graduate studies. The very first video that I made was about computer ethics, with a title of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c3qxRpnPgYE">Is CSGO Gambling Ethical?</a> Back then, gambling became infamous in the computer game Counter-Strike: Global Offensive, with some gaming influencers often advertising betting websites in their streams. This video explored the ethical concerns surrounding the promotion of gambling sites within a game played by a wide audience, including children, teenagers, and individuals who may be financially vulnerable.</p> <div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 mb-3"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/c3qxRpnPgYE" class="embed-responsive-item rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> <p>The second video was about database normalization. In this video, the first to fifth normal forms were discussed, along with examples. I opted for a more academic but engaging approach to this video, unlike the previous video. This was part of a group activity, so I volunteered to create the video while the others worked on the content. Upon receiving the initial draft of the script, it took me 20 minutes. In my mind, who wants to watch 20 minutes? I looked for similar explainer-type videos, and their approach was to explain a topic within a time limit, usually 5 or 10 minutes. I took this inspiration and modified the script to reach 10 minutes instead. After a few recording and editing sessions, the video was published to our class. The instructor, and our classmates, loved our work! From the comments we got, the consensus was that we were able to take a difficult topic yet discuss it concisely and engagingly as possible.</p> <div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 mb-3"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/v3N5PlbUHTs" class="embed-responsive-item rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> <p>The year is now 2017. I passed the first semester of my graduate studies, and I well on my way to the second semester. I was enrolled in the course Advanced Computer Systems. I thought this was going to be a boring subject, but our professor had other plans. The laboratory activities are both tedious, yet enjoyable. He had us explore <a href="https://samsungtizenos.com/">Tizen OS</a> and create a simple application—talk about obscure! Going back to the video, the assigned topic was concurrency. This time, I imitated the style of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Vsauce">Vsauce</a>. I’m a big fan of Vsauce and their approach to content creation. I had fun finding funny but related GIFs to insert in the video, especially the one at <a href="https://youtu.be/_pJCXxcX_r0?t=106">1:46</a> of the video.</p> <div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 mb-3"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_pJCXxcX_r0" class="embed-responsive-item rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> <p>The next video was a tutorial on how to inject DLLs, make windows unclosable, and decompile Visual Basic code. I know, that’s a lot. Please bear with me, as this video is over 15 minutes long, and full of jargon. For this video, since the requirement is to demonstrate the practical use of reverse engineering tools (and I had little time), I was not able to structure the video in any creative way. The video is just me, sharing my screen, and doing <a href="https://legend.octopuslabs.io/">R4ndom’s Beginning Reverse Engineering Tutorials</a>. This was my first foray into reverse engineering, and using tools such as RadASM, OllyDbg, and ILSpy.</p> <div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 mb-3"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/08N5iRhtd70" class="embed-responsive-item rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> <p>After I graduated my masters, content creation slowed down. It wasn’t until 2019 where I touched video editing software again. At the height of the pandemic, I was teaching at STI College Las Piñas. The current materials for my subjects wasn’t enough for me, I had to supplement it. Quizzes, assignments, and exams were adjusted to adapt to online learning modality. This included the way I approached lecturing. I had an opinion that an online class going over 3 hours is not conducive. Therefore, I recorded a sessions of myself explaining the topic, going over the software, what to do, what to click, etc. I then had students watch the video while doing the laboratory activity. This way, even if I’m not with them, the students can refer to the instructions in the video to accomplish the task. Mind you, not all students have access to a computer. I had to look for software that students can use with their existing devices (i.e. an Android phone).</p> <div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 mb-3"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ewNaKoSS4hg" class="embed-responsive-item rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> <p>While creating this blog post, I rewatched my recordings; Feeling cringe but at the same time nostalgia. Some of the videos I made was for an academic requirement, while others for my students. I’d like to think that, for a while, the videos I made helped out a struggling student. And for me, that’s all I need to know.</p> <p>Should I go back to making videos? We shall see.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="retrospective"/><category term="database"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="reverse-engineering"/><category term="operating-systems"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I made explainers and how-tos reverse engineering, cyber ethics, and others.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What SIEMs to be the problem?</title><link href="https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/wazuh-install/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What SIEMs to be the problem?"/><published>2026-01-08T21:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-08T21:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/wazuh-install</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/wazuh-install/"><![CDATA[<p>Visibility. That’s the problem.</p> <p>Security Information and Event Management, or SIEM, is a comprehensive system that provides real-time analysis of security alerts. This is an essential tool for security operation centers (SOC), whereby data generated by endpoints can be collected, aggregated, and analyzed. In this post, we will talk about <a href="https://wazuh.com/">Wazuh</a> and my experiences in installing it.</p> <p>Why Wazuh? Primarily, it’s open-source. Second, the ease of installation. Lastly, the name has a cool ring to it—sounds like something you’ll hear on a kids movie.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2026-01-08/mike%20wazowski.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2026-01-08/mike%20wazowski.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Mike "Wazuh"wski </div> <p>Now that’s visibility! Just like how Wazuh is able to see endpoint alerts, plus the user can see into its <a href="https://github.com/wazuh/wazuh">code</a>.</p> <p>Before we dive deeper into Wazuh, let’s first discuss <em>what</em> to protect. We have already talked about what a SIEM is and why companies should have it on their SOC, but it is important to know how many devices (or assets) we have, and which ones to secure. In reality, most organizations have a lot of computers, some of which may have different operating systems and configurations. It is possible that SIEM agents may not be compatible with some of the workstations. In addition, some SIEMs may charge fees for exceeding a certain amount of endpoints, or even on a per-endpoint basis. This increases total cost of ownership. BUT, there’s Wazuh! With its open-source to security, Wazuh is available at no cost! Huzzah!</p> <p>For testing, we will be securing four machines: one desktop, one laptop, and two virtual machines. The physical machines run on Windows 10, and the virtual machines run on <strong>Ubuntu 20.04</strong> via VirtualBox. The Wazuh server will be deployed on one of the Ubuntu VMs, whereas the other machines will have Wazuh agents.</p> <pre><code class="language-mermaid">flowchart LR
    subgraph "Windows Desktop"
        A[Wazuh Agent]
        subgraph "VirtualBox"
            subgraph "Ubuntu Virtual Machine"
                B[Wazuh Server]
            end
            subgraph "Ubuntu Virtual Machine"
                C[Wazuh Agent]
            end
        end
    end
    subgraph "Windows Laptop"
        D[Wazuh Agent]
    end
    B --&gt;|Monitors| A
    B --&gt;|Monitors| C
    B --&gt;|Monitors| D
</code></pre> <p>The first thing to set up is the Wazuh server on our Ubuntu 20.04 VM. Assume that all commands here are run as root user. Since it will be running on a fresh install on Ubuntu 20.04, we need to update the packages to minimize bugs and dependency errors. This can be done by running <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">apt update</code> followed by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">apt full-upgrade</code>. We need to install <strong>curl</strong> as well, by running <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">apt install curl</code>. We should be able to install Wazuh without much fuss.</p> <p>Wazuh has three central components: <a href="https://documentation.wazuh.com/current/installation-guide/wazuh-indexer/index.html">Wazuh indexer</a>, <a href="https://documentation.wazuh.com/current/installation-guide/wazuh-server/index.html">Wazuh server</a>, and <a href="https://documentation.wazuh.com/current/installation-guide/wazuh-dashboard/index.html">Wazuh dashboard</a>. These components will be installed, in order, on our Ubuntu 20.04 VM. Thankfully, the installation guides are straightforward. I was able to install these components without devolving into insanity. Seriously, it all took around 2 hours, with most slow downs due to Internet connection and occasional stuck processes.</p> <p>Now that the Wazuh server is up and running, next is to set a <strong>static IP</strong> address for the VM. When Wazuh agents are deployed, they will be connecting to the IP address of the Wazuh server. Therefore, dynamic IP address assignment via DHCP is not ideal. Under VirtualBox, I set the network adapter to bridged for the VM and took note of its MAC address. Next, I configured the DHCP settings on my router to set a static IP address on the MAC address of the VM. In this case, I used 192.168.1.125.</p> <p>Opening 192.168.1.125 will bring up the Wazuh login screen. Once logged in, we can now deploy our <a hred="https://documentation.wazuh.com/current/installation-guide/wazuh-agent/index.html">Wazuh agents</a>. From here, the setup will be GUI-based, where the requisite commands will be generated by the web interface. I just need to select the OS, enter the Wazuh server IP address and Wazuh agent name. I copied the commands and ran it on the endpoints. After initializing the Wazuh agent, I was able to see it on the Wazuh server.</p> <p>At this point, we have finished installing Wazuh. All that’s left is to explore its features, on which there are many. Expanding the hamburger, we get the following menus:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2026-01-08/wazuh-home.PNG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2026-01-08/wazuh-home.PNG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2026-01-08/wazuh-menu.PNG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2026-01-08/wazuh-menu.PNG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/2026-01-08/wazuh-custom-dashboard.PNG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/2026-01-08/wazuh-custom-dashboard.PNG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Lots to see and lots to click, but I got tired of reading documentation. So I searched for a guide on Youtube on setting a dashboard, and it lead me to MyDFIR’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QrcAhd5P7xw">tutorial</a> on creating a custom dashboard. I noticed that in his guide, he used the description “data.virustotal” on one of his visualizations. Essentially, he created data table of the top 5 alerts related to <strong>VirusTotal</strong>. I looked into it, and realized the power of Wazuh. It has the ability of becoming an eXtended Detection and Response (XDR). By adding the necessary scripts, Wazuh can handle File Integrity Monitoring and automatically remove malicious files on the endpoints. It’s like running an antivirus software on the machine. This is something I need to try, but wow. Wazuh, you’re awesome!</p> <p>That concludes my experiences with Wazuh. Overall, I’m quite pleased and can’t wait to try out its other features. You’ll be hearing more about this tool on this blog.</p> <p>If you’d like to learn more, I suggest you watch John Hammond’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7Gn1GY5CIxg">video</a> about Wazuh.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cybersecurity"/><category term="software"/><category term="linux"/><category term="installation"/><category term="wazuh"/><category term="ubuntu"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Experiences on installing Wazuh]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello, world!</title><link href="https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/first/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello, world!"/><published>2026-01-06T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-06T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/first</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jeanoskii.github.io/blog/2026/first/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my blog, where I post just about computer stuff (mostly). My current interests are on computers, programming, cybersecurity, gaming, and of course teaching.</p> <p>First of all, why make a blog? I figured that a blog on my website would be the best avenue for me to share my thoughts, opinions, and experiences. Here, I have control of the content and the way I want to present them. But people might wonder: How about Facebook or X? Well, I am privacy-conscious. I have always limited my social media use. When I’m not chatting with my friends on Messenger, I’d be checking Facebook marketplace, and that’s it. As a matter of fact, the marketplace would be the primary reason I’m not deactivating my Facebook account yet; such good deals!</p> <p>Now let’s talk how I went about creating this blog.</p> <p>There are numerous ways one can create a blog nowadays, from dedicated blogging platforms to completely custom blogs. I’m too frugal to subscribe to popular blogging platforms, but I’m also too lazy to code a blog from scratch. Then I remembered <strong>Github Pages</strong>; I used it to teach pull-based development where my students forked my Github <a href="https://github.com/jeanoskii/Software-Design-Prefinal-Exam">repository</a> and appended their own entry into the <a href="https://jeanoskii.github.io/Software-Design-Prefinal-Exam/">site</a>.</p> <p>However, Github Pages only allows static websites—no Wordpress here! I had to look for a static site generator, narrowing down my choices to Astro, Hugo, and Jekyll. Each option uses different programming languages: Javascript, Go, and Ruby respectively (all of which I know little of). But I had to choose, and since Jekyll has built-in support for Github Pages, I went with <strong>Jekyll</strong>. This meant I had to brush up on my Ruby skills.</p> <p>During college, we had a course on web development where we created an application using plain Ruby and Ruby on Rails. But that memory is a bit hazy. At this point, my priority is to publish a blog, not learn Ruby <em>to</em> publish a blog. So I looked into Jekyll themes, coming up with <a href="https://github.com/cotes2020/jekyll-theme-chirpy/">Chirpy</a> and <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/">al-folio</a>. Both themes frequented my search, but the choice boiled down to which one has better documentation and community support. Having an easy to understand documentation meant that I can set up, configure, and run my blog just by reading the manual; and a good community meant that more people could help me fix my terrible code. Therefore, I went with <strong>al-folio</strong>.</p> <p>So the tech stack goes like this:</p> <pre><code class="language-mermaid">flowchart LR
    A(Github Pages) --&gt; B(Jekyll) --&gt; C(al-folio)
</code></pre> <p>With this setup, I can quickly create a website while pretending to be coding in VS Code!</p> <p>As 2025 was ending, I kept thinking to myself that I needed to build a personal website. As 2026 starts, here I am with a finished blog post. Here marks the first out of the many posts in this blog. I am eager to share my knowledge, findings, and ramblings, only here on Jeano’s Journal.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="explainer"/><category term="blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My first blog post]]></summary></entry></feed>